Finding Aid for the Philippine Comics Collection LSC.2386
UCLA Library Special Collections
Philippine comics collection
2007-2018
UCLA Library Special Collections
LSC.2386
4.0 linear feet
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from a seller based in the Philippines, date of receipt unknown.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9997031821906533
Biographical / Historical
The comics format has been been a popular medium in the Philippines for decades. However, Ferdinand Marcos (1917-1989), nationalist president and corrupt dictator, heavily censored all publications. After Marcos was deposed by nonviolent revolution in 1986, independently published comics began to flourish. Like zines, the culture of independently published komiks was reborn in the 2000s due to advances in technology, when creating and sharing them became more widespread.
Scope and Content
The Philippine Comics Collection contains comics that showcase the creative minds of Filipino artists in the Philippines. It spans the years of 2001-2018, with the bulk of the materials dating 2011-2017 or are undated. They were created by various artists and are mostly collaborations. Many of the comics are self-published or published by small publishers like Pelikomiks Studio and Azhdarchid Komiks.
The komiks feature creatures of lore and incorporate Filipino culture into the storytelling. Content often mirrors the daily lives of the artists. Original Filipino superheroes -- often teenagers who find themselves being granted a superpower to save the people of the Philippines from attacks -- are also included.
The komiks are printed on glossy-paper, in color, or are scanned and printed in black and white.
Arrangement
The collection has been arranged chronologically by publication date.
Related Materials
Philippine Zine Collection (Collection 2281). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
- PINOY TOTOY PI-TOTOY, 2012-2013
  Scope and Contents
  Pinoy Totoy is the Captain America of the Philippines, and while he's much smaller and younger, he's doing the best he can at 12 years old. As a fan of superheroes himself, Totoy was not able to hold back the urge to step up to the call of justice when he saw other children in danger! The first issue of this Filipino comic book series was published by Bakal Komiks in 2012.
  Creators: Carlo Valenzuela; Patrick Enrique; Mel Casipit; Amos Villar
  Publisher: Bakal Komiks
  - Issue 1, 2012; 1 item
  - Issue 2, 2012; 1 item
  - Issue 3, 2013; 1 item
- Alamat Ni Manila Man, 2014 April
  Alamat ni Manila Man (The Legend of Manila Man) is a Taglish comic book series published in Manila, Philippines. The self-styled vigilante, Manila Man, is a mysterious urban superhero and defender. The story begins when Kendi, a recently promoted investigative journalist, connects her predecessor's recent murder to this vigilante.
  Creators: Mike Ignacio; RH Quilantang
  Publisher: Frances Luna III
  - Chapter 1: Bahagharing Itim, 2014 April 03; 1 item
- Bokunawa, 2013
  Bokunawa is a Philippine manga written in Tagalog that references Bakunawa, a sea serpent from Philippine mythology that swallowed the moon, to show a fictional fate of the Philippines under global warming, extreme drought, and extremely long days due to the sun not setting. People depend on scavengers, or pilots, who operate giant walking robots, to find water—a scarce resource because the land is drying up and the temperature is relentlessly rising.
  Creators: Raphael Cezar Casanova; Ruth Hanzessa F. Rodriguez; Freya Dy
  Publisher: Dr. RaCe's Publishing House
- Bruho Barbero The Barbarian, 2011-2013; 3 items
  Bruho Barbero is a Tagalog comic series that follows Bruno Barbaro, the strongest undefeated barbarian on the planet, as he transitions into living his life as Bruho Barbero, a mild-mannered barber, tired of fighting and violence. In each chapter, Bruho's attempt at a peaceful life is disturbed by warriors who want to be the first to defeat him. The first three issues of this series was published in 2011-2013 by Mengo Jam Cartoons in the Philippines.
  Creator: Rommel J. Estanislao
  Publisher: Mengo Jam Cartoons
  - Bruho Barbero The Barberian, 2011 November 19
  - Bruho Barbero The Barberian: Bururus, 2012 October 27
  - Bruho Barbero The Barberian: Man's Tender Trap, 2013 November 16
- CAUTION: DRUGS/SEX/ROCKn'ROLL, 2013 February; 1 item
  CAUTION: DRUGS/SEX/ROCKn'ROLL is a Tagalog comic book by Patrick "Rawwrr" Enrique that was published by Chain Mason in Manila, Philippines. In this comic book, an aswang (shape-shifting demon) made a binding life/death contract that gave a man who almost committed suicide a more lavish life. Enrique incorporated supernatural elements and used it as a creative and engaging way to shine a light on heavier topics such as suicide and drug addiction.
  Creator: Patrick Enrique
  Publisher: Chain Mason
- Si Heronimo alyas… HERO, Ang Bagong Bayani ng Marikina, 2010-2013; 2 items
  Si Heronimo alyas… HERO, Ang Bagong Bayani ng Marikina is a comic series created by Rommel "Omeng" Estanislao. It is about Heronimo, a vigilante hero who can't wait for the government to act on the crimes in Marikina, a city in the middle of Quezon, Pasig, and Rizal, and took up the alias HERO to save the community from crimes. HERO dons a lucha mask and uses unconventional weapons like yoyos, slingshots, and bottle caps as shuriken as he faces criminals like the Janitor Fish-Man and Chinese hit men.
  Publisher: Pocket-Size Indie Comics
  - Si Heronimo Alyas... HERO, Ang Bagong Bayani ng Marikina 3: Attack of The Janitor Fish- Man, 2013 April 12
  - Si Heronimo Alyas… HERO, Ang Bagong Bayani ng Marikina: Bugbugan Na!, 2010
- Labandero X, 2013 December
  Labandero X is a Tagalog comic created by Luigi Jocson or "Lui421," and published by Circle 421 in 2013. In this silly comic, our superhero Labandero X, uses cleaning products when attacking villains who aim to pollute the world.
- Liga ni Likeman
  Likeman Komiks, also known as Liga ni Likeman is a semi-autobiographical webcomic by Rasel Reyes that has been featured on the Philippine Daily Inquirer's entertainment section. Liga ni Likeman stars a social network addict cum super hero, Likeman. Likeman's companions are fellow netizens (internet citizens), including his mother, Lady Geegee, a YouTube sensation; Gamer Girl, his love interest; Ogie, his best friend who is as smart as a search engine; and Boy Inlab and Perly, a love duo who constantly fight on the internet.
  - Liga ni Likeman: Meet the Netizens, 1 item
  - Liga ni Likeman: Issue 1.1, 1 item
- Love Riot, 2011 November
  This is a comic book about Joey, a young boy who transferred to a new high school to curb his tendency to get into fights. However, he can't seem to escape violence as he runs into more trouble by fighting with a girl in his class. Eventually, he finds himself fighting alongside her as she battles her enemies.
  Creators: Cyrus Romanes; Frances John Haro; Edgar Torres Jr.
  Publisher: FHATE Comics
  - Love Riot: Chapter 1, 1 item
  - Love Riot: Chapter 2, 1 item
  - Love Riot: Chapter 3, 3 items
- Oh the Irony!, 2014; 2 items
  Contains comic books by Luigi Jocson, also known as "Lui421," and was published by Circle 421 in 2014. Every book contains a collection of not-so-usual stories of your not-so-usual everyday individuals living their not-so-usual everyday lives.
- Recreate, 2014; 1 item
  This is a comic created by artists under the aliases Yolak and Rawwrr. The story is fueled by power hungry, violent Lord Bel-shok who was captured by a powerful witch-queen of the Ishen forest. She is able to persuade Lord Bel-shok to comply with her demands to go to the Balete tree to see "him" by supplying Lord Bel-shok with the ancestral key to his land.
  Creators: Carlo Enaje; Patrick Enrique
- Tayuman: At Ang Mga Nagaalsang Tinapay, 2014
  This comic is about Tayuman, sentient pastries, a famous actress, and corrupt landowners. This playful comic exposes serious themes of exploitation and corruption, all while working with the theme of sentient bread.
  Creator: D. Jose
- The Hunting
  This comic follows the story of Zyo, a dark elf who found himself in Manila while on the run from white elves trying to hunting him down. In Manila, a place believed to be full of good food, people, and hiding places, Zyo is forced to use the sword that his late brother left him in order to fight against the white elves. Zyo unleashes its powers against the white elves. Can he be the true wielder of Naga, the sword of freedom?
  Creators: Daniel Collado; Miko Migriño; Laraine Gazmen; Mikhail Plata
  - The Hunting Chapter 1, 1 item
  - The Hunting Chapter 2, 1 item
- Windmills, 2011-2017
  Windmills is a semi-autobiographical comic with anamorphic characters that depict Josel Nicolas, the author, as a son, a friend, sometimes a lover, and a comic book artist. This semi-autobiographical comic shows the author's adventures in life and love through the lens of wisdom balanced with the ability to laugh at oneself.
  Publisher: Flipside
  - No. 4: I'm Gonna Be-ear, 2011 November 10; 1 item
  - No. 5: It's About Time, 2012; 1 item
  - No. 6: Stop Talking To Yourself, 2017; 1 item
- Darwin's Association of Delicious Evilness, 2012
  Darwin is a little, evil mastermind in the making. He has big plans of being a tyrannical dictator who will plant a giant bomb in the core of the earth. But Darwin is still an elementary school student, focusing on recruiting classmates who would be fit to be members of his evil association. This dark but mostly humorous comic brings bits nostalgia through its young characters, their street games, and the elementary school setting of the comic.
  Creator: John Carlo Clemente
  Publisher: Alamat
  - Darwin's Association of Delicious Evilness 1, 1 item
  - Darwin's Association of Delicious Evilness 2, 1 item
  - Darwin's Association of Delicious Evilness 3, 1 item
  - Darwin's Association of Delicious Reflection #4, 1 item
- ???, 2012
  The first comic, ???#1, is a compilation of mostly autobiographical strips about DJ Legaspi, except for a few, including one about Yeti Crab. ???#2 is a compilation of different comic strips that are purely autobiographical, providing a variety of stories about DJ's life, including stories about his dog, his childhood, his beard, and his wedding.
- Candido's Apocalypse, 2013; 1 item
  In this comic-book adaptation of Nick Joaquin's classic novel, teenager Bobby gets the power to see through people, literally. First, Bobby begins to see through people's clothes, until he begins to see through their skin and gaze upon their flesh and bones.
  Creators: Cyrene Ela; Natasha Ringor
  Publisher: 502 Komiks
- Maso, 2010; 1 item
  This is a superhero comic book, Filipino-style. Maso, a well known superhero works with BANGIS, a league of villains, to save his girlfriend. Burdened by shame, he takes out his frustration on other heroes and starts to smear his image in the eyes of the Filipino people. Maharlika, a former American superhero literally knocks some sense into Maso, but trouble is around the corner. A special operations squad of heroes attack the two of them because Maharlika turned his back on the United States.
  Creator: Ramil A. Ibay
  Publisher: dGREAT
- Manosaur, 2013; 2 items
  Manasaur is the lone survivor of the meteor shower that wiped out the dinosaurs on Earth, and now, he tries his best to fit in with the modern human world.
  Creator: Elbert Or
- Goons, 1 item
  Goon is a comic about Zeus, a man hired to be a henchman for a league of villains. All proceeds from the sale of comic were donated to the victims of Typhoon Yolanda.
  Creator: Mary Or; Hinchel Or; Joey Pastrana
- PAD KOMIKS
  PAD is an abbreviation for Pagibig, Aksyon, Dilim-a three part comic series about Boy, who falls in love with a girl who later disappears. Despite the journey Boy takes to save her, they still end up breaking up, teaching Boy the lesson that sometimes, the things that make us happy have always been right besides us.
  Publisher: Ardie Aquino
  - Unang Yugto Pagibig, 1 item
  - Ikalawang Yugto Aksyon, 1 item
  - Ikatlong Yugto Dilim, 1 item
- Sanduguan, 2007-2013; 4 items
  Sanduguan is a fictional comic book universe of Filipino superheroes based on native Filipino myths and stories. The universe is split into three factions: Sandugo, Katipunan, Inc. and the Zodiac Force. The concept of the Filipino hero team, Sandugo, was loosely based on sanduguan (blood ritual) done by Katipuneros who vowed to fight against the Spanish occupation in the Philippines. In these Sanduguan issues, Sandugo battles against the villain Vital and his Acolytes for the Eye of Bathala, or the eye of the Creator.
  Creator: Gener A. Pedriña
  Publisher: Kathang Indio Studios
  - Sanduguan #12, 2013 March
- Para Fierra
  This comic centers around Donny, a young man who boards a jeepney driven by Mang Aldo, who agrees to drop him off after making his usual late night rounds. Little to Donny's knowledge, the jeepney shuttles passengers made up of demons, angels, incarnations, and anthropomorphisms to places beyond the human world. What Donny doesn't consider is the price for a ride to heaven, hell, and back.
  Creators: Fidelis Tan; Kiko Dans
  - Route 1: Night Riders
  - Route 2: Impyerno
- Ang Superhero Na Stainless: Boy Bakal, 2010-2013; 1 item
  Boy Bakal follows the story of 10-year-old Rayan Keen, a child prodigy and owner of a successful chain of junk stores scattered across the Philippines. His superhero costume is made of strong, sturdy stainless steel that helps him fight against crimes and villains. This volume includes 10 chapters of the superhero comic book.
- I Hate Mornings, 2013; 1 item
  This is a comic book about an author of comic books and his struggle to write about crime fighting heroes that are also realistic. The author thinks it is absurd to both be a superhero and be real. However, the reason he hates mornings so much is that he unknowingly turns into a crime fighting hero at night after falling asleep and wakes up not remembering anything. It is ironic because the realistic superhero he struggles to write about is actually himself.
  Creator: Kenneth Yu
- Shatter Space - Space Mando, 2012; 1 item
  Shatterspace is about a space-faring nomad who believes he is the last of his kind. Not having seen a sign of life for a while, he checks a planet out in search of intelligence but discovers more than he bargains for.
  Creator: Nelz Yumul
  Publisher: Dark Bulb Comics
- Ang Hari ng Komyut, 2017; 1 item
  The King of Commute rises above the long lines, the hassle, the rudeness, and the traffic during his endeavors on public transportation. This compilation of single-page comics shows the everyday journeys of the King of Commute as he travels through the city by taking jeepneys, buses, trains, and van services with kindness and grace.
  Creator: Lizette Daluz
  Publisher: Anino Comics
- Opismeyts, 4 items
  Opismeyts was originally a webcomic that started out with the title Model Employee. After being rebooted a few years later, Opismeyts became successful, and started getting printed in The Daily Inquirer and made into compilation comic books. The comics revolve around the daily lives of so-called "model" employees and their boss.
  Creator: Ramark Masangcay
- Lindol #1, 2017; 1 item
  In the New World, ravaged by earthquakes and tsunamis, people have to adapt to the aftermath that wiped out society's structure. We follow the story of a former marine and an art conservator, who go out of their way to find bare necessities as they navigate through the rubble of the Philippines. The purpose of this comic, aside from entertaining its readers, is to raise awareness about earthquake preparedness for this overlooked threat to society.
  Creators: Tedi Gustilo Villasor; Randy Valiente
  Publisher: Tedi31.com
- Bravos: Cebu
  In a world where only the Philippines has superheroes, those with powers serve their country as Bravos. Bravos: Cebu City features the story of Lea, who gets recruited to attend Maharlika High, a government-accredited educational facility for the exceptionally gifted. Leah has no interest in becoming a Bravo, but accepts the scholarship because of the financial support. This chapter falls under the same universe as Bravos: Manila, despite having different writers, artists, and art styles.
  Creators: Elbert Or; Cy Vendivil; Jem Bernaldez
  Publisher: Studio Salimbal
  - Cebu, 1 item
  - Manila, 1 item
    Creators: Paolo Chikiamco; Butch Mapa; Wilson Dela Fuente
- Ang Butiki At Ang Pagong, 2017; 1 item
  A comic written in Baybayin, the ancient script used by Tagalogs in the Philippines. The comic is a modern rendition of a Tinguian folklore about a turtle and a big lizard who went to the field of Gotgotapa to steal ginger. The responsible and slow turtle warns his friend to be careful, but the reckless lizard does not listen. Despite getting the ginger, the lizard gets caught by a human, and the turtle gets away.
  Creators: Cy Vendivil; Koi Carreon
- Ang Badass Na Buhay Ni Lam-Ang, 2014-2015
  This is a modern rendition of an Ilokano epic poem about Lam-ang, an extraordinarily strong warrior. Like any epic journey, the story starts with the birth of Lam-ang, in which he names himself using his extraordinary ability to talk as a newborn. Shortly after, he begins searching for his father, which ends up in disappointment and anger because the Igorots have beheaded him. Lam-ang erases the Igorot tribe from existence, settles on a mountain top, and then ventures out to find his purpose. Eventually, Lam- ang chooses a wife, but cannot marry her until he defeats all of her suitors. The original version of this epic has been passed down orally, evolving over the course of Philippine history. This version's bold style does not shy away from showing Lam-ang's extremely strong powers and how he uses them.
  - Ang Paglapag Ng Epikong May Laman At Buto Sa Mundong Ibabaw, 2014; 1 item
  - Sayaw Sa Kamay Ni Kamatayan, 2015; 1 item
  - Ang Mga Gutom Na Buwitre, 2015; 1 item
  - Libog Ng Digmaan, 2015; 1 item
- Ligaya #1 and #2, 2 items
  A comic about two sad kids and the ghost of a national hero that tackles the problems that slip into people's everyday lives.
  Creators: Addie Onday; Faye Bergonia
- The Lolita Chronicles
  These comics follow Lolita's life in the office as a financial analyst as she faces strict bosses, haughty co-workers, and a messy love life. Maria Criselda Santos sprinkles in Filipino gay lingo in the comic as a way to create humor in the dialogue.
  Creators: Maria Criselda Santos; Stacee J
  - First Love Never Deadmas, 2015; 1 item
  - Beauty And The Beastmode, 2016; 1 item
  - AWOL To Remember, 2016; 1 item
  - All The Love In The Fort, 2016; 1 item
- Espiritista, 2016
  Espiritista is a comic about a school that teaches students how to defend and fight against malevolent Engkantos, or ancient spirits. In these chapters of Espiritista, Samuel is facing off with his old mentor, who has betrayed him and the school, and has sided with the Engkanto.
  Creator: Niño Balita
  Publisher: Pagsapuge Comics
  - 4: Tears and Cobwebs of the Past, 1 item
  - 5: Forbidden and Unforgiven, 1 item
  - 6: Motives and Tactics, 1 item
- Native, 2016
  Native is a comic book series by Julius Villanueva that is about how the human race is resisting violent alien colonies that have invaded the Earth. It shows how humans have either sided with, or have taken up arms against the violent bug-like creatures despite being outnumbered and overpowered.
  Publisher: Azhdarchid Komix
  - Issue 1, 2016; 1 item
  - Issue 2, 2016; 1 item
  - Issue 3, 2016; 1 item
  - Issue 4, 2016; 1 item
  - Issue 5, 2017; 1 item
  - Epilogue, 2017; 1 item
- Antingeros, 2015; 2 items
  In these comics, four childhood friends each obtain an anting-anting, a magical charm that gives power and protection, by remembering and following a neighborhood grandpa's stories about them. These friends walk a careful line between power, ambition, violence, and treachery with their borrowed powers from their anting-anting.
  Creators: James Bernardo; Geonard Yleana; Carlo Cruz
- Higante, 2013
  This comic book series is about two homeless brothers, Obet and Toti, who scour garbage heaps for food. While hiding in a drainage pipe, Obet finds a mysterious liquid that turns him into a giant when he drinks it. Not free from the binds of poverty, Obet uses his new powers to get him and his brother food, as well as to protect other people in poverty.
  Creator: Geonard Yleana
  Publisher: Pelikomiks Studios
  - A Monster Grows From the Wasteland, 2013; 1 item
  - A Mountain of Appetite, A Big Fistful of Hate, 2013; 1 item
  - Of Mice, Monsters & Men, 2013; 1 item
  - The Drink of the Gods, 2013; 1 item
  - Into the Hole, 2013; 1 item
- Aswang de Manila 1 and 2, 2 items
  These comic books are about Maria and Jose, classmates whose paths cross when they acknowledge that they both sense and see aswangs. Throughout this story, the different types of aswangs are introduced, and their purpose and relationship to humans are revealed.
  Creators: Kevin Samala; Nadine Narag; Ianthe Pimentel
  Publisher: Blue Indie Komiks
- Agila, 2015-2016
  Agila is a comic series about Juan José, a college professor of Philippine history, who was chosen by the spirit of a mysterious wooden mask that provides him with superhuman abilities.
  Creators: José Victor Fuentecilla; Arjohn Perdon; JC Panililio
  - Agila 001, 2015 August; 1 item
  - Agila 002, 2015 November; 1 item
  - Agila 003, 2016 March; 1 item
- Dakila Metronom
  Brandon is a geek who has loved comic books, RPGs, and cosplay his whole life. At 17 years old, he becomes the world's first superhero, complete with the cape, mask, skintight outfit, and amazing superpowers. Metronome shows the emergence of Dakila as a superhero, but also as a young boy who is trying to fill the shoes of a savior.
  - Dakila: Buwan Part 1 of 3, 1 item
    Creators: David Hontiveros; Jason Confesor
  - Dakila: Buwan Part 2 of 3, 1 item
  - Dakila: Metronom Part 1 of 3, 1 item
    Creators: David Hontiveros; Nonie Cruzado
  - Dakila: Metronom Part 2 of 3, 1 item
    Creators: David Hontiveros; Romnick Magbanua
  - Dakila: Metronom Part 3 of 3, 1 item
  - Dakila: Siyudad Part 1 of 4, 1 item
    Creators: David Hontiveros; Pyotr Mutuc
  - Dakila: Kadena Part 1 of 3, 1 item
    Creators: David Hontiveros; Patrick Flores
  - Dakila: Kapalaran Part 1 of 3, 1 item
    Creators: David Hontiveros; Bibo Reyes
  - Dakila: Lumilim Part 1 of 3, 1 item
    Creators: David Hontiveros; Elmer Cantada
  - Dakila: Makadaot Part 1 of 3, 1 item
    Creators: David Hontiveros; Carl Corilla
  - Dakila: Dahas Part 1 of 4, 1 item
    Creators: David Hontiveros; Gaston Garcia
- Incognito, 2 items
  Intramuros is the strongest country in the world due to its advanced technology and because of a wall that keeps its people safe. When a mysterious killer and thief dubbed Anino infiltrates Intramuros, the safety and economy of the country becomes compromised. These comics are the 3rd and 5th installations of the Filipino comic series.
  Creator: Faye Villanueva
  Publisher: Kawangis Komiks
- Ella Arcangel, 2016-2017
  Ella Arcangel is a mananambal, a person that can treat both natural and supernatural maladies. She lives in Barangay Masikap, an area ridden with poverty, crime, and hardships. In addition to watching out for supernatural occurrences, she is concerned about the well-being and future of her barangay and its residents who are living in poverty.
  Creator: Julius Villanueva
  Publisher: Azhdarchid Komiks
  - Oyari sa Dilim, 2016; 1 item